As an introduction to this theory section,
I want to start with a very cool
and very high-level overview about the JavaScript language.
Just so you get a first overview
of most of the things that we need to learn
in order to eventually master JavaScript.
And this is gonna be a long lecture,
so get ready for a crazy ride.
And I want to start by coming back to that first definition
that I gave you on JavaScript,
where I told you that JavaScript
is a high-level, object-oriented,
multi-paradigm programming language.
Now this is of course 100% correct,
but it's also really just the surface,
the tip of the iceberg.
So what about this definition?
JavaScript is a high-level, prototype-based,
object-oriented, multi-paradigm,
interpreted or just-in-time compiled,
dynamic, single-threaded,
garbage-collected programming language
with first-class functions
and a non-blocking event loop concurrency model.
Wait, what?
Is this some kind of joke?
Well, yeah, it kind of is actually,
I just packed as much information as possible
about JavaScript into one unreadable sentence, just for fun,
but besides fun,
this also gives us a great opportunity
to unpack all of this in order to get a first peek
into all the stuff that we're gonna learn about JavaScript
throughout the course.
And this is not to intimidate you. It's really not.
I just want you to get the big picture
before really getting started
and also introduce some topics
that are just good to know,
because getting the big picture before diving deep
is in my opinion, an amazing learning technique.
So with that being said, let's unpack this now a little bit.
So these are the nine JavaScript topics
that we're briefly gonna talk about in this lecture,
slightly reordered.
And starting with the high-level part,
as you might already know,
every program that runs on your computer
needs some hardware resources,
such as memory and the CPU to do its work.
Now, there are low-level languages, such as C,
where you have to manually manage these resources.
For example,
asking the computer for memory to create a new variable.
On the other side,
you have high-level languages such as JavaScript and Python,
where we do not have to manage resources at all
because these languages have so-called abstractions
that take all of that work away from us.
This makes the language easier to learn and to use,
but the downside is that programs will never be as fast
or as optimized as for example, C programs.
Now, one of the powerful tools
that takes memory management away from us developers
is garbage-collection,
which is basically an algorithm
inside the JavaScript engine,
which automatically removes old, unused objects
from the computer memory
in order not to clog it up with unnecessary stuff.
So it's a little bit like JavaScript has a cleaning guy
who cleans our memory from time to time
so that we don't have to do it manually in our code.
Next up, JavaScript is an interpreted
or just-in-time compiled language.
And again, we will learn more about this in this section,
but what you need to know for now
is that the computer's processor
only understands zeros and ones, that's right.
Ultimately, every single program needs to be written
in zeros and ones, which is also called machine code.
And since that's not really practical to write, is it?
We simply write human-readable JavaScript code,
which is an abstraction over machine code,
but this code eventually needs to be translated
to machine code.
And that step can be either compiling
or interpreting.
This step is necessary in every single programming language
because no one writes machine code manually.
In the case of JavaScript,
this happens inside the JavaScript engine.
Now, one of the things that makes JavaScript so popular
is the fact that it's a multi-paradigm language.
In programming, a paradigm is an approach
and an overall mindset of structuring our code,
which will ultimately direct the coding style and technique
in a project that uses a certain paradigm.
And this definition still sounds kind of abstract,
but don't worry,
it will become more clear as we move on.
Now, three popular paradigms are;
procedural, object-oriented,
and functional programming.
So procedural programming is what we've been doing so far,
which is basically just organizing the code
in a very linear way,
and then with some functions in between.
Now about object-oriented programming
and functional programming,
I will talk about them in a second.
Also, we can classify paradigms as imperative
or as declarative, but again, more on that later.
Now, many languages are only procedural
or only object-oriented
or only functional,
but JavaScript does all of it.
So it's really flexible and versatile.
And so we can do really whatever we want with it.
It's our choice. We can use whatever paradigm we want.
And in this course, I will show you how to use all of them.
So, about the object-oriented nature of JavaScript,
it is a prototype-based, object-oriented approach.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, first, almost everything in JavaScript is an object,
except for primitive values
such as numbers, strings, et cetera.
But arrays, for example, are just object.
And we already saw that in practice, right?
Now, have you ever wondered why we can create an array
and then use the push method on it, for example?
Well, it's because of prototypal inheritance.
Basically, we create arrays from an array blueprint,
which is like a template and this is called the prototype.
This prototype contains all the array methods
and the arrays that we create in our code
then inherit the methods from the blueprint
so that we can use them on the arrays.
And this, what I just explained to you
is actually a huge oversimplification,
which might still sound confusing.
And that's the reason why there is a whole section
on object-oriented programming with JavaScript
later in the course.
But since this is a big overview lecture,
I wanted to first introduce this topic right here.
Next up, JavaScript is a language
with first-class functions,
which simply means that functions
are treated just as regular variables.
So, we can pass functions into other functions
and we can even return functions from functions.
And this is extremely powerful
because it allows us to use a lot of powerful techniques
and also allows for functional-programming,
which is one of the paradigms
that we just talked about before.
And in fact,
we have already used the power of first-class functions
without knowing that they are called first-class functions.
So remember this piece of code that we wrote
for closing the modal window that we built before.
So right here, we pass the closeModal function
into the addEventListener function
as if it was just a regular variable, right?
And actually not all languages have first-class functions,
but JavaScript has, and it is amazing.
Believe me, it's really, really helpful.
Next, I said that JavaScript is a dynamic language
and dynamic actually means dynamically-typed.
So as we've already seen,
in JavaScript, we don't assign data types to variables.
Instead, they only became known
when the JavaScript engine executes our code.
Also, the type of variables can easily be changed
as we reassign variables.
And this is basically what dynamically-typed means.
Now there is a lot of controversy if this is good or bad,
but this is just how it works.
Now, the same is not true
for most other programming languages,
where we have to manually assign types, to variables.
And this then usually prevents bugs from happening,
which is the reason why many people say that JavaScript
should be a strongly-typed language as well.
And if you yourself want to use JavaScript with types,
then you can always look into TypeScript.
But anyway, let's now finally talk about the single-thread
and the non-blocking event loop concurrency model.
Now this is a really complex topic
and probably the most complex one of the whole course,
which is why it's kind of at the end of the course.
And therefore,
I'm not gonna go into specifics here just yet,
but instead I will just define some things here.
First, what actually is a concurrency model?
Well, it's just a fancy term
that means how the JavaScript engine handles multiple tasks
happening at the same time.
No, okay. That's cool.
But why do we need that?
Well, because JavaScript itself runs in one single-thread,
which means that it can only do one thing at a time
and therefore we need a way of handling
multiple things happening at the same time.
And by the way, in computing,
a thread is like a set of instructions
that is executed in the computer's CPU.
So basically, the thread is where our code
is actually executed in a machine's processor.
All right. But what if there is a long-running task,
like fetching data from a remote server?
Well, it sounds like that would block the single thread
where the code is running, right?
But of course we don't want that.
What we want is so-called non-blocking behavior
and how do we achieve that?
Well, by using a so-called event loop.
The event loop takes long-running tasks,
executes them in the background
and then puts them back in the main thread
once they are finished.
And this is, in a nutshell,
JavaScript's non-blocking event loop concurrency model
with a single thread.
It sounds like a mouthful for sure
but in the end,
it really just compresses to this.
Just keep in mind that, again,
this is a huge oversimplification that we will come back to.
All right.
And this actually rounds up this overview lecture.
I know there was a ton of stuff to take in,
but I hope that you still learned a thing or two here.